<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest censure of the immodest letter to a dissenter, upon occasion of His Majesty's late gracious declaration for liberty of conscience by T.N. a true member of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>T. N., True member of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N76</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11817191</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11817191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 542:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest censure of the immodest letter to a dissenter, upon occasion of His Majesty's late gracious declaration for liberty of conscience by T.N. a true member of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>T. N., True member of the Church of England.</author>
                  <author>T. N., True member of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Halifax, George Savile, --  Marquis of, 1633-1695. --  Letter to a dissenter.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1685-1688 : James II). --  His Majesties gracious declaration to all his loving subjects for liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49539:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49539:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Modeſt CENSURE OF THE Immodeſt Letter TO A DISSENTER, Upon occaſion of His Majeſty's late Gracious DECLARATION FOR <hi>Liberty of Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> T. N. <hi>a true Member of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed with Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49539:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49539:2"/>
            <head>A Modeſt Cenſure of the Immodeſt Letter to a <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Letter to a Diſſenter by <hi>T.W.</hi> which you ſent me the laſt Week, I have peruſed, and find it very ſpitefully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoring to perſuade the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> 1. To ſuſpect the Kindneſs of His Majeſties late Gracious Declaration; And 2. To uſe their Intereſt againſt the Eſtabliſhment of that Liberty by Law, which he therein Graciouſly Indulges to all His Subjects.</p>
            <p>The Letter it ſelf is like a <hi>Pleaſure-Boat,</hi> richer in the <hi>Trimming</hi> than in the <hi>Lading.</hi> The Language of it, I confeſs, is very ſmooth and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, but his Suggeſtions are too ſowre and ſevere, and his Style too ſharp when it touches upon the Government; nor could any Man <hi>ſpeak</hi> ſo <hi>Evil of Dignities</hi> (as he do's) <hi>without Scandal,</hi> even tho' it could be ſaid <hi>with truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character <hi>T. W.</hi> gives of himſelf in the firſt Page, is, That he is a Proteſtant at large, <hi>who will not let his thoughts for the</hi> Public <hi>be ſo ty'd or confin'd to any Subdiviſion of them, as to ſtifle his Charity, which is become ſo neceſſary at this time</hi> for their mutual <hi>Preſervation;</hi> and yet one would think by <hi>his Letter,</hi> that his <hi>tender Conſcience</hi> had catch'd the <hi>Cramp</hi> with his <hi>too much ſtretching,</hi> and that he was inſenſible of what dropt from his Pen; for after he had <hi>charg'd the King</hi> with the worſt of Crimes, One that would not only falſifie his Word with them <hi>at firſt,</hi> but give them <hi>no Quarter</hi> at laſt, and drawn his Picture like one of the Squint-ey'd <hi>Italian</hi> Pieces, which preſent us with a <hi>Saint</hi> on the one ſide, and a <hi>Monſter</hi> on the other, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> with <hi>haughtineſs, and the rigidneſs of her Prelates</hi> towards Diſſenters, and the <hi>Spirit of Perſecution,</hi> he would make us believe, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. that no ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was in his Style, nor any <hi>Gaul</hi> mingled with his <hi>Ink,</hi> becauſe <hi>Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was the only thing he intended,</hi> and that he would not <hi>expoſe any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Men, how ſtrong ſoever the Temptation might be, and how clear the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49539:3"/>Proofs to make it out,</hi> whereas in truth, for what appears to me by <hi>his Lower, his Skill ſeems</hi> Chiefly <hi>to lie in a quick Hand for Lancing and Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;</hi> and <hi>pag.</hi> 3. he <hi>is the worſt at Healing</hi> of any Writer that ever pretended to it; Never any State-Mountebank offer'd more improper <hi>Plaiſters for Tender Conſciences,</hi> and ſhould he ever ſet up his Proteſtant Bills, I ſhould rather ſend the Diſſenters to his Friend <hi>Burnet</hi> or <hi>Fergu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> than to him, for a Cure of their Diſtempers, neither of which ever Preach'd up more <hi>Vengeance againſt the Church of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. than he has done, at which, he muſt forgive me, if I am both <hi>ſurpris'd</hi> and <hi>provok'd,</hi> and <hi>ſtartled to have an Eye upon</hi> him; for when a <hi>Man comes ſo quick from the one Extreme to the other in</hi> ſuch an <hi>unnatural Motion,</hi> he has taught me how much it <hi>concerns me</hi> to be upon <hi>my guard,</hi> pag. 3. I can as little gueſs at the <hi>Author's Religion,</hi> as at his <hi>Name;</hi> he ſeems to me to be ſome degraded Courtier, who having been outed of his Employment, begins to Harangue upon what he has loſt, and to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, not his Reaſon, but his Revenge, reſolves to plume his towring Fancy over the King's and Churches Intereſt, and doubts not but to make a Prey of <hi>both</hi> in the end, if by his Seditious Methods he can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a good Correſpodence between the King and <hi>his two Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> when he ſhall think ſit to call them, or at leaſt to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>more conſiderable</hi> than now is he, by being <hi>troubleſom;</hi> whatſoever he be, I dare ſay he is no legitimate Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor will ſhe ever give him her Bleſſing, till he beg the King's and her Pardon for the Diſloyalty of this Letter.</p>
            <p>Now, tho' I am not at all <hi>accountable</hi> for the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> whoſe <hi>Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> from the Church of <hi>England</hi> I have always <hi>lamented</hi> and <hi>condemned;</hi> yet my <hi>juſt zeal</hi> for that Church, makes me <hi>impatient</hi> to find one who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to <hi>be of her Communion,</hi> by his ſly Inſinuations Libelling both the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Her</hi> too. The Father's danger makes <hi>Craeſus's dumb Son</hi> to ſpeak; and on what better occaſion can I (hitherto a ſilent Spectator) begin to ſpeak, than for the Vindication of the Father of my Country, and my dear Mother, which will, I hope, Apologize for all my other Weakneſſes, whilſt I repreſent to you, how ill it becomes a <hi>Member of the Church of England,</hi> to perſuade <hi>any Subjects</hi> into an <hi>ill Opinion</hi> of <hi>their Prince,</hi> and to repreſent <hi>Her</hi> as an <hi>Enemy to his Clemency</hi> to any of his Subjects, of what Perſuaſions ſoever in Religion.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Firſt Deſign of this Letter, which is to perſuade the Diſſenters into a ſuſpicion of his Majeſties Kindneſs. This is the firſt thing he offers to their Conſideration, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. What reaſon they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49539:3"/>have to ſuſpect their <hi>new Friends.</hi> Now by the ſequel of the Diſcourſe it is manifeſt, that by their <hi>new Friends</hi> he means thoſe whom the <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration repreſents for their Friends,</hi> and that being the King's Declaration, it's the <hi>King and his Council,</hi> whom he muſt needs mean by their <hi>New Friends,</hi> and conſequently it is the <hi>King's Expreſſion</hi> of Kindneſs to them in <hi>his Declaration,</hi> that he would have them to <hi>ſuſpect.</hi> But how ill ſuch a <hi>Deſign</hi> becomes a <hi>Member of the Church of England</hi> is very apparent. For ſhe hath always taught her Children not only, not to Reſiſt, but to Honor the King, and conſequently never allows them to ſpeak evil of, much leſs (upon weak Surmiſes) to charge him with the <hi>baſeſt Diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity,</hi> viz. a Deſign to <hi>cheat all that truſt</hi> him. At his Majeſties <hi>firſt approach</hi> to the Throne, we all unanimouſly concluded it our Duty to <hi>believe and truſt</hi> to his <hi>Royal Promiſe,</hi> and ſeem'd with a becoming Zeal to ſuſpect the Loyalty of all ſuch as <hi>diſtruſted</hi> in the leaſt the ſincerity thereof. And what reaſon can we have to be weary of well doing?</p>
            <p>There was a time when we thought <hi>any,</hi> the <hi>leaſt diffidence</hi> in the King's <hi>repeated Promiſes</hi> to be the moſt <hi>diſobliging thing</hi> in the World, and ſuch as would be <hi>reſented</hi> accordingly; we had then <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> enough to ſtick to our <hi>Principles,</hi> and ſhall we now be ſo <hi>eaſily frighted</hi> out of our <hi>Wits and Loyalty,</hi> as ſome <hi>Neuter-paſſive-Royaliſts</hi> are, whom we ſee driven from their <hi>old Principles,</hi> as ſome <hi>ſilly Birds</hi> are from <hi>their</hi> Food by <hi>Men of Clouts,</hi> an <hi>empty windy Noiſe,</hi> or a <hi>ſenſleſs Scare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crow</hi> dreſs'd up by any <hi>Pamphleter,</hi> who envies their Happineſs. O fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh <hi>Galatians,</hi> you did run well at firſt, who has hindred you of late from holding on in the ſame good old way of Duty to God and the King, who has been Indulgent to you <hi>beyond a Preſident,</hi> and done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to diſoblige you, but in keeping you from <hi>biting and devouring one another</hi> you know not why? And <hi>who will harm you, if you be followers of that which is good?</hi> I am one of thoſe, who am <hi>ſo valiant</hi> as to have none of <hi>thoſe Fears and Jealouſies about me</hi> which our <hi>Author</hi> ſpeaks of, nor do I think, that he himſelf who acts <hi>this timorous Part</hi> before the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter,</hi> do's <hi>believe</hi> himſelf, but only <hi>pretends</hi> it, in purſuance of ſome <hi>other dark Deſigns,</hi> for which his <hi>Letter</hi> (as <hi>black</hi> as it is) would <hi>bluſh</hi> if they ſhould be brought to light. The King has done all things that in him lies, to create a Confidence in him, and all things conſpire to give us Eaſe, Satisfaction and Security, if <hi>we</hi> are not <hi>wanting</hi> to our ſelves; and therefore we have great reaſon to be extreamly pleas'd and oblig'd, and to ſhew the Nation (that part of it which is <hi>without,</hi> as well as that <hi>within</hi> the Pale of the Church) that we are ſo; for this is ſuch a piece
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49539:4"/>of <hi>Good Manners</hi> as will be a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5+ letters">
                     <desc>•••••…</desc>
                  </gap>ian Duty,</hi> and not a <hi>Court Complement;</hi> and the <hi>Vertue</hi> of it is the gloater, becauſe it is now become <hi>neceſſary</hi> for the preſervation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the juſtification of her avow'd <hi>Principles of Loyalty.</hi> We have hitherto been taught <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>uncondition'd Obedience</hi> for Conſcience ſake, and practis'd it in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>black Bill of Excluſion,</hi> for which our <hi>Divinity</hi> as well as our <hi>Policy</hi> was arraign'd by ſome ſuch <hi>Proteſtants at large,</hi> as the <hi>Author</hi> of this Letter, at leaſt our <hi>want of Foreſight</hi> and <hi>palpable Inadvertency.</hi> And ſhall we not <hi>now retain</hi> the ſame <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences void of offence towards God and Man?</hi> Wherein hath our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sovereign been <hi>worſe than his Word</hi> to us? Ours is the <hi>National Religion</hi> ſtill, our <hi>Revenues</hi> and <hi>Privileges</hi> are as <hi>great</hi> as ever, our <hi>Churches</hi> are as <hi>well fill'd,</hi> our <hi>Sacraments</hi> as <hi>much frequented,</hi> our <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> as much <hi>reſpected,</hi> at leaſt, as they were in the <hi>late King</hi>'s time, the <hi>preſent State</hi> of <hi>the Church of England</hi> is as <hi>flouriſhing</hi> as ever we knew it, and ſo Exemplary is the <hi>King's Self-denyal</hi> in the Exerciſe of <hi>his own Religion,</hi> that he hath not taken any <hi>one Church</hi> or <hi>Chappel</hi> throughout the Kingdom for himſelf, or thoſe of his own <hi>Communion,</hi> which was ever dedicated or appropriated <hi>to ours by Law,</hi> ſo little cauſe do's he give us of Repining, and ſo much of Rejoycing and Gratitude.</p>
            <p>The firſt Reformers in <hi>Germany</hi> (as whoever peruſeth <hi>Sleidan's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries</hi> may obſerve) repeated their Addreſſes of Thanks to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, as oft as he renew'd his Promiſe of Protection: and when ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing had been done in the Chamber of the Empire, that ſeem'd to them an <hi>infringement</hi> of <hi>former Grants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sleid. Comment. l. <hi>10.</hi> Edit. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentor. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>292.</hi>
               </note> and ſome ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted <hi>his Deſign</hi> to oppoſe them by <hi>a War,</hi> upon his <hi>Gracious Declaration, in a Letter</hi> to them, of his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſtill to Protect them, they made a <hi>new Addreſs of Thanks</hi> for delivering them from their <hi>new Fears,</hi> by <hi>renewing his Promiſe.</hi> And tho' in like Circumſtances ſome of <hi>the Church of England,</hi> who had <hi>put ſuch Bounds to their good Breeding,</hi> as our <hi>Author</hi> cautions others to do, prov'd <hi>reſty, and refus'd</hi> to <hi>repeat their grateful Acknowledgments</hi> for his Majeſty's <hi>late Gracious Declaration</hi> to <hi>Protect them in the firſt place,</hi> leſt ſuch an <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>uſual</hi> piece of <hi>Good Manners</hi> ſhould be interpreted to be the <hi>Approbation</hi> of the <hi>King's whole Declaration;</hi> yet <hi>others</hi> acted more <hi>agreeable</hi> to the forecited Preſident, by <hi>renewed Addreſſes on that</hi> occaſion: whereby they declar'd, that they <hi>ſtill believ'd him ſincere</hi> in, and <hi>faithful</hi> to his Promiſe, notwithſtanding all the <hi>Suſpicions,</hi> that by <hi>Malecontents</hi> were whiſper'd to the contrary.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49539:4"/>And let the World judge, whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have not acted <hi>more agreeable</hi> to the Loyal Principles of the Church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England,</hi> than <hi>this Author,</hi> who not only ſuſpects the Ingenuity of his Sovereign's Promiſe, but writes on purpoſe to propagate his Suſpicions among the reſt of his Fellow Subjects. They cannot by <hi>Words</hi> or <hi>Writing</hi> treat the <hi>King worſe,</hi> who have an <hi>opinion of his Idolatry,</hi> than <hi>he</hi> do's; nor can the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> her ſelf be <hi>worſe at Healing</hi> than he is, who <hi>pretends</hi> ſo much to it; and therefore 'twill be fit for <hi>Diſſenters</hi> to pauſe upon his Methods, before they believe them, or have ſo good an opinion of <hi>them</hi> or <hi>him,</hi> as not to be <hi>upon their guard</hi> when he accoſts them, like one fully reſolv'd that his <hi>over-merits of the Crown</hi> ſhould never do him prejudice. And if it be <hi>Moral Parricide</hi> to wound the Reputation of him whom theſe three Kingdoms deſervedly Honor for their <hi>Common Parent,</hi> and <hi>Father of their Country</hi> (except his licencious Pen can give us a Diſpenſation for that too, and ſecure us by a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> to the Divine Law, that God will not think the worſe of us for it) the true Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> will not take <hi>his Judgment</hi> to be any <hi>intellectual Standard,</hi> nor be ſeduc'd into ſo <hi>crying a Sin</hi> by his ſubtil Devices. His <hi>whole Letter</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays ſuch <hi>groundleſs Fears and Jealouſies</hi> of the King, and drives on an <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſo very deſtructive to the <hi>Crown and Church of England</hi> (of which I profeſs my ſelf to be a Member) and declaims with ſo deep a Reſentment againſt <hi>her</hi> Perſecuting Humor, that how <hi>ſincere</hi> ſoever his Addreſs may ſeem to them, who judge of his Sincerity by the <hi>clearneſs of his Style,</hi> more than by the <hi>weight of his Reaſons,</hi> and have Minds pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to be deceiv'd by his malicious Inſinuations, becauſe he tells them; that they <hi>come from a friendly</hi> Hand; yet I am one of thoſe who have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Faith nor Charity enough to believe Him to be either a <hi>good Subject,</hi> or a <hi>true Son of the Church of England.</hi> And I muſt beg his pardon, if I am both <hi>ſurpris'd and provok'd,</hi> to ſee that in the <hi>Condition we are now put into by the Laws, and the ill Circumſtances we lie under,</hi> by having the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Diſſenters, and the want of Loyalty to the King laid to our charge; We who pretend to be <hi>true Sons of the Church of England,</hi> ſhould endeavor to <hi>make our ſelves and others more uneaſie, and obnoxious to the Preſent Authority</hi> which God hath ſet over us. And methinks he ſeems to be <hi>ſore put to it,</hi> when out of a deſire of <hi>revenge</hi> he teaches <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> to run to <hi>their old Methods of Embroyling the Kingdom, with too much haſte to conſider all the Conſequences,</hi> and hopes to <hi>inſtigate us</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>run along with them to the ſame exceſs of riot.</hi> They muſt be <hi>unreaſonably valiant</hi> who dare follow ſuch Advice, and ſuch an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49539:5"/>extraordinary Courage at this <hi>unſeaſonable time, to ſay no more, is too dangerous a Vertue</hi> to be <hi>commended</hi> by any <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>good Subject</hi> He had need to go upon <hi>certain Evidence,</hi> who charges <hi>his Neighbor,</hi> much more <hi>his Prince,</hi> with ſiniſter Intentions and Treachery in his Kindneſſes; otherwiſe he violates the <hi>natural Obligations</hi> of Juſtice and Charity, as well as the <hi>Loyal Principles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> What then may we judge of <hi>T. W.</hi> who in the <hi>Name of the Church of England</hi> takes ſuch pains to perſuade the Diſſenters that their New Friend, their Gracious King, is a treacherous Man; eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the weakneſs of thoſe Reaſons wherein he grounds his Suſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which come now to be Examin'd?</p>
            <p>The Firſt I find <hi>pag.</hi> 2. That the Diſſenters are not the King's <hi>Choice,</hi> but his <hi>Refuge,</hi> after the Church of England <hi>hath refus'd his Courtſhips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he might the better <hi>teach Diſſenters</hi> to caſt off their <hi>new Lovers,</hi> he perſuades them that they had before made their ineffectual Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and been <hi>ſcornfully rejected</hi> by them, and muſt either <hi>drive</hi> a <hi>Contract</hi> with <hi>them,</hi> or deſpair of <hi>good Fortune</hi> for ever; and that if their ſudden Paſſion have not blinded them, they muſt needs ſee, they Court them not <hi>for Love</hi> but <hi>Intereſt.</hi> Which to me ſeems (to ſpeak <hi>as ſoftly</hi> as may be) a very rude Inſinuation, ſuch as <hi>T.W.</hi> would never have us'd, had he not wanted <hi>the Bounds to his Ill Breeding,</hi> which he would have others put to <hi>their Good Breeding.</hi> An Inſinuation that equally wrongs the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Church of England,</hi> who would no more be guilty of <hi>putting her King to his Shifts,</hi> than <hi>ſuch a King</hi> as <hi>ours</hi> would ſtoop to ſuch <hi>mean</hi> ones. Did not his innate Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and Compaſſion to his Subjects (perhaps to an Exceſs) prompt him to it, I ſee no <hi>neceſſity of his Circumſtances</hi> that could drive him to <hi>Court</hi> the more deſpicable part of them, as the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are reputed to be.</p>
            <p>What Courtſhips of the King, or from Men of his Communion, the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath <hi>rejected,</hi> I know not; and what <hi>Applications</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall be made to <hi>her in the firſt</hi> or <hi>ſecond</hi> place, I doubt not but ſhe will receive with that Reſpect and Duty which becomes her.</p>
            <p>But the next Inſinuation is more conſiderable;</p>
            <p>That there is no Alliance between Infallibility and Liberty, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. That it is the <hi>bringing together</hi> the two moſt <hi>contrary</hi> things in the World; and that their Abſolution for the <hi>mortal Sin of promiſing it,</hi> is to be had upon no other Terms than <hi>their Promiſe to deſtroy them;</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49539:5"/>which they will be the eaſier tempted to do, becauſe in truth they have no Inclination, no not ſo much as to give them any Quarter, but to Uſher in Liberty for themſelves under that Shelter; for which he refers them to Mr. <hi>Coleman's Letters, and the Journals of Parliament,</hi> where they may be convinc'd, if they can be ſo miſtaken as to doubt; And that they cannot forbear, even in the height of their Courtſhip, to let fall <hi>hard words</hi> of them, becauſe their <hi>cruel Nature</hi> is not to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd</hi> from ſtarting out, as diſdaining to ſubmit to the Uſurpation of Art or Intereſt. Now to ſhew the weakneſs of all he ſuggeſts on this Head, I ſhall offer theſe Two Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether there be not ſome difference between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> offering Liberty to Heretics, and a Gracious King of <hi>that</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, promiſing <hi>Eaſe to his Subjects?</hi> For however cruel toward Diſſenters, the Principles of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can be ſuppos'd to be, the Sweetneſs of his Nature may correct <hi>them,</hi> or the <hi>Generoſity of his Courage</hi> over-bear them. A Papiſt may be a Friend to Liberty, and a known Enemy to Perſecution, and our <hi>preſent King,</hi> upon whom you ſquint, <hi>was</hi> always ſo, and <hi>ever will</hi> be. There is no Religion ſo bad, but there may be very <hi>good</hi> Men among the Profeſſors of it; however inexorable to thoſe it calls Heretics, Popery can be thought to be, there are <hi>many</hi> Papiſts (we know) merciful Men. And who more worthy of that <hi>Character</hi> than <hi>this Prince,</hi> whoſe <hi>Clemency</hi> hath hitherto ſo flatly given the Lye to all former Characters of a Popiſh Succeſſor? Were it not then more fair, and juſt, to believe this Declaration ſincere, becauſe made by ſo good a Prince, than to ſuſpect it of Treachery, becauſe we have a bad opinion of his Religion? And that the Obligations of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion</hi> will prevail more with him to be <hi>ſtill merciful</hi> in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and <hi>faithful to his Promiſes,</hi> than the ſuppoſed Principles of Popery, to betray thoſe that relie on his Royal Word, which is as cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as his Coyn?</p>
            <p>Our Confidence in our Prince's Word, which is as <hi>ſacred</hi> as his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, will be our greateſt Prudence. We can never truſt our Lives and Fortunes in ſafer Hands than his, to whom by our Addreſſes we have ſo unanimouſly tendred them, at which his Enemies and ours are not a little netled. If we are any of us afraid of his Power, it is not his Fault but our own; take not mine, but St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s word for it, <hi>Do that which is good, and you ſhall have praiſe of the ſame;</hi> but if you do that <hi>which is evil,</hi> you may well be <hi>afraid your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>make us ſo too,</hi> for he <hi>bears not the Sword in vain, but is the Miniſter of God for revenge, to execute
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49539:6"/>wrath upon them that do evil.</hi> He has oblig'd us ever ſince he came to his Throne in ſuch a Princely manner, as to puzzle our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as well as our Gratitude, we are as ſafe and ſecure as we can deſire to be, whilſt he lives, and he is content we ſhould be as <hi>true to our God</hi> as to <hi>our King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And yet it is no <hi>ſuch Paradox</hi> as he pretends, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. that <hi>Popery ſhould be</hi> a Friend to <hi>Liberty,</hi> or the Pretenders to Infallibility <hi>tolerate Diſſenters,</hi> and live peaceably with them. That there have been great Cruelties acted by Men of that Communion, is out of queſtion; and <hi>this Author</hi> acknowledges (<hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 16.) that there have been <hi>Prelates of our Church</hi> too rigid: And as theſe are now convinc'd of their Error, in being ſevere to Diſſenters, (as he ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 1.) is it not poſſible that <hi>thoſe</hi> may ſee <hi>their Miſtake</hi> too? eſpecially ſince they <hi>pretend to Infallibility</hi> only in Matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> not in <hi>Fact,</hi> or the Conduct of their Practice. However, what hath been practis'd in other Places, is not altogether unfeazable among us. For beſides the Toleration of the Three Religions in <hi>Germany</hi> by the Treaty of <hi>Munſter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> (whom he will not deny to be an authentic Hiſtorian) in a late Account he gives of <hi>his Travels</hi> (<hi>pag.</hi> 289.) acquaints us, That <hi>Charles Lewis,</hi> late Prince Palatine, ſeeing of what advantage <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is to the Peopling of a Country, not only allow'd the Three Religions (the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſt, Lutheran,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi>) to be Profeſs'd there, but built a Church for them all Three, which he call'd <hi>The Church of the Concord;</hi> in which they all had (in the Order above ſet down) the Exerciſe of their Religion; and yet he maintain'd the Peace of his Principality ſo entire, that there was not the leaſt Diſorder occaſion'd by this Toleration. The like Toleration, without the leaſt Diſorder, the ſame Perſon tells us (<hi>p.</hi> 286.) is maintain'd at <hi>Francfort.</hi> And who is ſo great a Stranger abroad, as not to know, that the Cantons of <hi>Switzerland</hi> are made up of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> all united by their common Intereſt, notwithſtanding their Differences in Religion. And in two of thoſe Cantons (as the forecited Author aſſures us, <hi>pag.</hi> 27.) <hi>Apenzel</hi> and <hi>Glaris,</hi> both Religions are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, and capable of equal Privileges. And in ſome Bailiages, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd in common by the Cantons of <hi>Bern</hi> and <hi>Friburg</hi> in the Wars with <hi>Savoy,</hi> the two Cantons name Bailiffs by turns, and both Religions are ſo equally tolerated, that in the ſame Church they have both Maſs and a Sermon, and that with ſuch equality, that on <hi>one Sunday</hi> the Maſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins and the Sermon follows, and on the next <hi>Sunday</hi> the Sermon begins and the Maſs comes after it, without any diſorder or murmuring.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49539:6"/>
            <p>Theſe Inſtances are undeniable Evidences of the conſiſtency of <hi>Popery</hi> with <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> ſo that whatſoever Arguments can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to prove the contrary, are like <hi>Zeno</hi>'s Reaſonings againſt the poſſibility of Motion, confuted by the noiſe of <hi>Diogenes</hi>'s Tramplings, that diſturb'd his Lectures. It's in vain to argue that Papiſts cannot live peaceably where they are tolerated, or that they cannot tolerate others, where they have Power, ſince we can produce ſuch plain <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact</hi> both for the one and for the other. And ſince ſome Papiſts live peaceably with Proteſtants, and allow them to enjoy equal Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with themſelves, in the Exerciſe of Religion, a Pretence to Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility may be <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with <hi>Liberty,</hi> without building upon a <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Paradoxes,</hi> which he ſays is <hi>ſo dangerous;</hi> And this Suggeſtion is no concluding Argument, that the King intends to deceive the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and oppreſs all other Parties but his own.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen plainly, that the Papiſts do allow Living and Liberty to Proteſtants under them in <hi>Germany,</hi> by the Treaties of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Oſnaburgh,</hi> that they have alternative Election of Magiſtrates, and that neither Party do's, or is <hi>allow'd</hi> to diſturb other in the Exerciſe of their Religion in Publick, and that all others with a free Conſcience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Diſturbance</hi> or <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> ſhall Exerciſe their Religion in <hi>their own Houſes</hi> privately, and in the Neighborhood, where, and as often as they pleaſe; and therefore we have leſs ground to ſuſpect their doing it ſincerely here in <hi>England,</hi> where 'tis more their Intereſt, becauſe the King is ſo great a <hi>Lover of his Country,</hi> that he will never give the <hi>Power</hi> into thoſe <hi>few Hands of the Catholics,</hi> againſt the <hi>more numerous Party of his Proteſtant Subjects,</hi> and conſequently <hi>more able</hi> to Serve him againſt his <hi>potent watchful Neighbors,</hi> who would catch at ſuch an opportunity to ſtir up. Wars againſt him both Abroad and at Home. The King knows that he is ſure of the Hearts and Hands of all the true Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and he will never oppreſs them to make them <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> or to loſe <hi>their Services.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His next Suggeſtion of <hi>Suſpicion</hi> is from the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of this new Friendſhip, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. whom for Arguments ſake (deſigning to make them <hi>out of love</hi> with them, and to queſtion their <hi>Integrity</hi>) he ſuppoſes to be <hi>ſuſpicious Perſons.</hi> And are not all ſuch Hypothetical Arguments as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily blown away by ſuppoſing the contrary? I will eaſily grant him, that they are bad men, who Preach up Anger and Vengeance againſt the Church of <hi>England, pag.</hi> 5. But as the King diſcourages all ſuch kind of Diſcourſes in his own Chaplains, ſo we may charitably ſuppoſe, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49539:7"/>whoever uſe them, are none of his Inſtruments, who deſigns Eaſe to Diſſenters without Vengeance againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And therefore they who act that cholerick Part, are, I am ſure, none of the King's Inſtruments. You maliciouſly ſuggeſt, that the Mediators of this new Alliance have been formerly Employ'd in Treaties of the ſame kind, and there detected to have acted by Order, (by <hi>whoſe</hi> you do not tell us, but leave us to our gueſs, nor by whom ſo detected) and to have been impower'd to have given Encouragements and Rewards, and that this is an Argument to ſuſpect them. Nay, you come <hi>farther</hi> home, and inſinuate that the King hath given them a Commiſſion, and not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly a Diſpenſation in the Caſe of Truth, when it may prejudice <hi>his Service</hi> that Employs them, <hi>(Calumniare audacter aliquid haerebit)</hi> and would have the Diſſenters look upon them as Embaſſadors ſent to lie Leiger, <hi>i. e. Ad mentiendum Reipublicae cauſâ.</hi> You ſuppoſe there are ſome Men <hi>Employ'd</hi> by him who have Means and Authority to perſuade by Secular Arguments, and that they in <hi>purſuance</hi> of that Power, have ſprinkled Mony among the Diſſenting Miniſters, and that this is an Evidence of the Deceit intended; and that many unfortunate Men (whoſe Names you will not be tempted to diſcover) have fall'n under this Temptation, who for fear their Frailty ſhould be diſcover'd and expos'd, will continue it, whoſe Arguments, tho' never ſo ſpecious, are to be ſuſpected, becauſe they came from them who have Morgag'd themſelves to ſevere Creditors, who expect a rigorous obſervation of the Contract, let it be never ſo unwarrantable; and theſe are the Dog-Stars of all the malignant Influence againſt which you declaim: But how came you to be privy to all this, unleſs you were once <hi>One of the ſame Cabal,</hi> and one who hir'd them to Preach up Anger and Vengeance againſt the Church of <hi>England?</hi> If there be any ſuch inflaming Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in the Conventicles, I will eaſily grant it to be as unſeaſonable as your Pamphlet, and they who act this cholerick Part, upon what For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture ſoever they are oblig'd to it, are very corrupt Men, no doubt, (almoſt <hi>as bad</hi> as your ſelf) and their Wages in the next World, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance, will be <hi>Death, and that Eternal,</hi> whatſoever they hope to get by it in this.</p>
            <p>The laſt of his <hi>Inſinuations,</hi> is from the <hi>great Endeavors</hi> that are us'd <hi>to Court Addreſſes,</hi> it being improper for the Benefactor to preſs Men to be Thankful, and an Argument that he intends to Snare them by their own Acknowledgments, as he ſuggeſts <hi>pag.</hi> 7. But to allude to his own Compariſon (a little after,) our Great Sovereign is not of ſo <hi>mean</hi> a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49539:7"/>Spirit, as to ſollicit for Love-Letters; He entertains the Grateful with Reſpect, but when did he ever Court the Ungrateful to give him Thanks? I have heard of Inſtances, wherein he forbad the moving of ſome to Addreſs that needed Courting, but never the contrary, except from this Author. It may be ſome Perſons, aſham'd of the Ingratitude of ſome of their own Party, were active to remind them of their Duty, but it is an incredible Calumny, that the King ſhould Court, much leſs Threaten, or cauſe to be Courted or Threatned (as this Man affirms, <hi>pag.</hi> 7.) any to Thank him for thoſe Favors, which not the expectation of Applauſe, hut his own innate Goodneſs hath produced. No, it's the more Glorious to be Thankful to him, becauſe ſuch is his Clemency, that with ſafety to our Temporal Intereſt we may be Ungrateful.</p>
            <p>I have heard indeed, that as many Biſhops as were then in <hi>London,</hi> did meet together, upon the ſenſe of their Duty to draw up an Addreſs of Thanks to the King; which having done, they ſent down Copies of it to ſome of their Brethren, one of which, and he as good a Caſuiſt, and as far from the Court as any of his Bench, having ſeriouſly perus'd and conſider'd it, gave this Judgment of it, <hi>That he highly approv'd it, as pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Penn'd, and ſuch an Acknowledgment of his Majeſties Signal Favors to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and all her Members, as their Gratitude and Duty indiſpenſably oblig'd them to pay.</hi> And he not only Subſcrib'd it chearfully himſelf, but us'd his beſt Diligence to procure Subſcriptions of the Clergy to it in his Dioceſe, and having receiv'd ſome nameleſs Letters (like this of <hi>T. W.</hi>) to diſſuade him from Addreſes, and among the reſt thoſe call'd the <hi>Oxon. Reaſons,</hi> he anſwer'd them all, to the ſatisfaction of all thinking Men, who ſaw them, and concluded, That he ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them that look'd like a Reaſon againſt it, only ſome groundleſs Fears and inſignificant Jealouſies; and that if the Clergy at this time, and in theſe Circumſtances we now are, ſhould generall and obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny in an humble Addreſs to give his Majeſty Thanks for ſo Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Promiſe of preſerving that <hi>ALTAR</hi> from being overthrown, at which yet he did not worſhip, he fear'd it would give him too much cauſe to ſay, That he had little Reaſon to protect them, who ſo peremptorily refus'd, as the Motion of their own Biſhop, to Thank him for it. And others wiſh'd, that the niceneſs of particular Men, where in truth no need was, did not at laſt hazard the whole; and ſo indeed it muſt have done, had not his Majeſty, in imitation of HIM whom he Repreſents among us, of his great and undeſerv'd Mercy been <hi>Kind to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankful,</hi> and according to his accuſtom'd Goodneſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49539:8"/>ſpar'd the Church for the ſake of the ſmaller viſible number that were in it; ſo great Grace may, if they are not paſt cure, heal their Infidelity and Revolt from their Duty, eſpecially when they are thus invited to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and adhere to a Prince, of whom we have had ſufficient Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that he will no more recede from his Promiſe, than he would fly from his Enemy in the Day of Battel. If the nature of Thanks be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable a Conſequence of being pleas'd or oblig'd, (as our Author confeſſes) and they will preſently ſhew themſelves in Looks, Speeches, Writing and Actions; then they from whom Thanks do not naturally flow, upon ſo juſt and great an Occaſion, are to be reckon'd among the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe unholy and unthankful Men, whom the Apoſtle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells us will ariſe in the latter days, who not only will give no Thanks, but have none to give, If our Obligations were leſs, and our Senſe of the Religion of Gratitude, as little as our Authors; yet I wonder he ſhould be offended at ſuch an innocent and uſual piece of Good Manners. He would make us ſuſpect him for one of the Members of <hi>Forty Eight,</hi> who Voted no more Addreſſes to be made to the King; for he is ſo mightily netled at theſe weekly Addreſſes of Loyal Men, from all Parts of the Kingdom, that he would make us believe, if we conſulted the Bills of Mortality, we ſhould find ſome numbers murder'd by them. He tells us that the Prieſts (who are not proper Secretaries for the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) made the firſt Draughts of them; A Scotchman would take the liberty to tell him, that he were very good Company, and an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would wonder how he came to be ſo privy to this Secret, unleſs he were at their Elbows when the Prieſts Indited them. Theſe extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Acknowledgments (as he calls them, extravagantly enough) which he pretends all the Poſt-horſes are tir'd with carrying Circular Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſolicit, give us a Copy of his Countenance; And that where Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions cannot delude, Threatnings are employ'd to fright Men into a Compliance (but where, or by whom, he knows not); And that the manner of getting them did extremely leſſen their value; And that the Thanks which fill'd the Gazetts, were either Trifles or Snares, which either ſignifi'd nothing, or a great deal more than was intended by them who gave them. By all which he proves himſelf a greater Maſter of his Pen than his Paſſions, that his Wit is more than his Manners, and that his Republican Zeal has, like a Cormorant, devour'd his Charity to his Fellow Subjects, and his Loyalty to his Prince. Do not his Objections to his Majeſties Belief now hinder him from ſeeing his Vertues, whilſt he inſtigates others to diſcredit and diſobey him? One would think he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49539:8"/>himſelf, who pretends to be a Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> made but a Jeſt of the Doctrin of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> whilſt he is ſo fearful of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of his Fellow Subjects, to the King's ſo juſt and reaſonable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation from them. Is not our Peace at Home, and our Prince's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation abroad, of more value than to be hazarded for want of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, as he calls it? If I did not think it a Task too hard for me, to perſuade a Man ſo bewitch'd with a turbulent Spirit as he is, to grow more peaceable; and thought he were not ſo far gone in his new Paſſion, but that he would hear ſtill; I would not be diſcourag'd from diſſuading him to relie on a Death-bed Repentance. If he have not engag'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Ways of Faction, in an Aſſociation beyond Retreat, and be not hurry'd on by his firſt Heat, I would requeſt him to look back upon what he has written, before it be too late, and not ſacrifice the true public Intereſt of the Nation to his private Revenge; which will ſpeak him a Man of good Morality and Underſtanding, as well as a great Wit: But I fear, that as he has betray'd too much Weakneſs, in enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and propagating theſe groundleſs Fears and Jealouſies, by which he ſpeaks his Spleen, and not his Conſcience; ſo he will ſhew too much Obſtinacy to forſake and recant them, being none of thoſe who thinks himſelf oblig'd to obey for Conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>And now I leave <hi>T. W.</hi> to review his own Reaſons, and conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be not too weak to acquit him from Uncharity and Diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in charging his Sovereign with Treachery in the Declaration of his Mercy to Diſſenters, or (which is much the ſame) in perſuading Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters to ſuſpect him: And the worſt I wiſh him is, that the ſenſe of his Guilt may make him a true Penitent. I proceed to the Second Part of his Deſign, which is</p>
            <p>To excite the Diſſenters to uſe their Intereſt againſt the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Liberty by Law, which his Majeſties Clemency hath In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged to them.</p>
            <p>If he can perſuade the Diſſenters to throw the King's Declaration of Indulgence at his Head, which is within the Bounds: he has ſet to his Good Breeding, and to throw away their preſent Advantages, and to ſtay for the Liberty of the public Exerciſe of their Religion till the Parliament allow it them, and to ſatisfie themſelves with thoſe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Advantages of which they can hardly fail in the next probable Revolution, if by an unſeaſonable Activity they loſe not the Influence of their good Star, which promiſes them every thing that is proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for that all things ſeem to conſpire to their Eaſe and Satisfaction, if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49539:9"/>by too much haſte to anticipate their good Fortune, they do not deſtroy it; Such a prevailing Eloquence as this, would ſpeak him an Orator beyond compare, and would give us cauſe to conclude by the Effect it had upon them, that the Diſſenters had not yet been ſo long reſtrain'd from their Liberty, as to have any ſtrong Appetite to enjoy it again: but the <hi>Indians,</hi> I believe, may as ſoon catch Monkies with a Mouſetrap, as he can draw in the Diſſenters with ſuch a dull Device as this, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy themſelves by uſing their Intereſt againſt the Eſtabliſhment of that Happineſs by a Law, which his Majeſties Clemency hath already Indulg'd them. For this purpoſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. he inſinuates the Irregularity of the Declaration in point of Law, which whether it be ſo or no, is certainly not ſo fit to be determin'd in a Pamphlet, as in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> which already hath given its Opinion in favor of the Prerogative. And after that, it is (methinks) no ſmall Preſumption to Cenſure the King's Actions as irregularly done, which proceed upon ſuch ſpecial Verdict for their Legality.</p>
            <p>As the King do's not need the Diſſenters Thanks to juſtifie his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration in point of Law, ſo neither do the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doubt of the Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his Power of Diſpenſing with them for his Time, but they deſire to have the Royal Favor made more laſting to them by a Law.</p>
            <p>Beſides, is it not very ſtrange, that Men ſhould generally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the King a Right to Diſpenſe with Penal Laws againſt Theft and Murder, which are founded upon a Divine Sanction, yet queſtion his Right to Diſpenſe with thoſe againſt a Conventicle, which can make no ſuch Pretences? Or that this ſhould lay a Foundation for the breach of all Laws (ſo ſaith this Writer, <hi>pag.</hi> 9.) and that ſhould not? Or that Diſſenters ſhould look like Council Retain'd againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> for thankfully receiving the Benefit of this, and Felons never be ſo Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd for that? But if (as he preſumes to affirm) the Declaration be irregular, it's not a little difficult to comprehend, how this becomes an Argument againſt Endeavoring to have the Liberty granted by it, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by a Law; ſince the Invalidity of their preſent Grant ſhould in all reaſon make them more ſollicitous for ſuch a Confirmation, as may preſerve the Liberty they are ſo deſirous to enjoy.</p>
            <p>His Arguments to me ſeem very weak againſt this mighty Power of Diſpenſing, which needs not the Juſtification of a Parliament, tho' the Penal Laws and Teſt want their Repeal, which I hope they may have in good time, without endangering or deſtroying our Religion, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties. But our Author thinks this a proper time to put the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49539:9"/>in Pickle, for ſome other Generation that can better digeſt it than the preſent; and in purſuance of his Deſigns, he makes the Laws ſpurn againſt their Maker; which is not the way to ſecure our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but to make our Church the more odious, by practiſing that which ſhe profeſſes to abhor: She has taught her Sons to believe, that no Power on Earth can give Licence for the doing of that which is <hi>Malum in ſe,</hi> an Offence in its own nature, and ſo declar'd by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law; but that <hi>Malum prohibitum,</hi> which in its own nature is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and becomes an Offence only becauſe ſome Law of the Land makes it ſo, ſhe thinks may be diſpenſed with, according to the King's Diſcretion, whom ſhe allows to be the proper Judge of Public Neceſſity. 'Tis impoſſible for Human Law-makers, who have no pretence to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, or a perpetual Divine Aſſiſtance, to foreſee all particular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, Miſchiefs, and Inconveniences which may happen in particular Circumſtances by or from the making of any particular Law; And therefore there muſt be ſome Power always viſible and in being, to Suſpend or Diſpenſe with ſuch Laws, as the Public Good and Safety of the People, or an emergent Neceſſity requires, which is by Law in the King, who is the Head of the Public Good, and the Fountain of Juſtice and Mercy; which Power is ſo united to his Royal Perſon, that he cannot transfer, give away, or ſeparate the ſame from himſelf, as all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> reſolv'd, (<hi>Lord Coke lib.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 36.) nor can he bar himſelf from that which is ſo inherent in him, and inſeparably annex'd to his Royal Perſon, no not by an Act of Parliament; for by ſo doing he would ceaſe to be King, (<hi>Coke lib.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 14.) the moſt he can do, is only to agree, that he will not uſe that Right but in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Caſes and Occaſions, when in his Princely Wiſdom he ſhall find it neceſſary for the Public Good: Nor is his reaſſuming to Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ſuch a Right, any Breach of his Promiſe or Oath at his Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a making uſe of that Condition imply'd in his Agreement, as to ſuch particular Caſes, and ſuch preſent Circumſtances. The King can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Repeal, and totally make void the Law by his own ſingle Power without a Parliament, but Relax, Suſpend, and Control it for a time, with reſpect to the Advantages or Neceſſities of his People he may, which is a temporary Repeal, or the laying the Law down to ſleep for a time in a legal way, which is a ſufficient Diſcharge to them who are Commiſſion'd under him, and by his Authority, to put them in Execution. Our Author knows, that the ſtrict keeping of <hi>Lent</hi> is enforced by great Penalties in our Laws, <hi>viz.</hi> 2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49539:10"/>
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 6 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 33. 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 5. and yet that the King was never que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd the Power of Diſpenſing with them all, either by Judges, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, or Parliament, but his Power in theſe Points has had an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Admittance, with a <hi>Nemine contradicente;</hi> and why then ſhould it be arraign'd only in Diſpenſing with thoſe Penal Laws relating to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion againſt Conventicles or Recuſants?</p>
            <p>In his next Attempt he ſeems to imitate the laſt and deſperate Shift of the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> when he took his eldeſt Son that ſhould have Reign'd in his ſtead, and offer'd him a Burnt-offering upon the Wall, to move the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by that Inſtance of his Miſery and Deſperation, to pity him, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.27. For, to move the Diſſenters Compaſſion, he ſacrifices the Reputation of his own Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> confeſſing, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. that ſhe out of revenge, for the rough uſage ſhe met with from the Diſſenters in the time of their Reign, upon the late King's Reſtauration made the Penal Laws againſt them; and leſt they ſhould imitate her Faults, he cautions them againſt ſeeking to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd, by attempting the Repeal of them. Whether this Inſtance of his Deſperation will be as ſucceſsful as the King of <hi>Moab</hi>'s, and prevail with his Adverſaries to quit their Advantage, I know not; but if it do, they are certainly very good-natur'd Adverſaries in both the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptations of the Phraſe, whether it denote the exceſs of their Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the defect of their Underſtandings. Some Men are ſo Spider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirited, as to ſuck Poyſon out of the ſweeteſt Flowers: For my part, I cannot think ſo ill of thoſe Great Men, who ſuffer'd with ſo much Chriſtian Patience for their Loyalty, as that they came from under the Rod breathing nothing but Revenge againſt their Perſecutors. It is a more juſt Account, and ſuitable to the Character of their Piety and Loyalty, that what they then did in Severity againſt the Diſſenters, was not from private Revenge, but from the Neceſſities of the Kingly Government, to which the Diſſenters had been very pernicious, and which they thought could not be ſafe, at that time, without the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of them.</p>
            <p>But if his Suggeſtion were true, that the Penal Laws againſt Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were made out of Revenge, what Argument is this againſt their endeavoring the Repeal of them? Unleſs it were Criminal to ſeek for a Releaſe from the Injuries that Revenge hath laid upon them, or a Sin to flee from the Avenger of Blood into the City of Refuge. To Reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate Injuries is a Crime, but to ſeek for Protection and Eaſe from them is not. And I ſee not but that the Diſſenters, if they be (according
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49539:10"/>to his Character of them, <hi>pag.</hi> 10.) Men of good Morality and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, may thus argue, <hi>The Church of</hi> England, <hi>after the late King's Reſtauration, ſacrific'd its Intereſt to Revenge, in making the Penal Laws againſt us, and therefore we may lawfully, for our own Eaſe, endeavor the Repeal of them, and not loſe the preſent Opportunity to reſcue our ſelves out of her avenging Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to mend the matter, he tells us, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. that the Common Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger had now ſo laid open the Miſtake, that all former Haughtineſs of the Church of <hi>England</hi> toward them, is for ever extinguiſh'd, and hath turn'd the Spirit of Perſecution into a Spirit of Peace, Charity and Condeſcention. A fit Argument to infer this Concluſion, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Diſſenters ought not to endeavor their own Eaſe. Whereas this ſeems the more natural Inference, That therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> will now joyn her Endeavors with them for the Repealing of thoſe Laws, the Enacting and Execution of which he imputes to a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Perſecution.</p>
            <p>But to do the Church of <hi>England</hi> right againſt theſe malicious Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, I am ſure her Principles are againſt Perſecution, or any thing of Violence and Cruelty toward any for Religion; And whatever may have been the Practices of ſome rigid and violent Perſons of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, the moſt Wiſe, Pious and Learned of them, have ſtill declar'd it unlawful to make any Sufferers for their Conſcience, unleſs where it interferes with the Peace and Safety of the State: They would have no Man's invincible Perſuaſion in Religion be made High Treaſon, as it was in Sir <hi>Tho. More</hi>'s and the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s Caſes. The Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in Religion that are inauſpicious to the Government, they think ought to be puniſh'd, not becauſe they are Errors in Religion, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Seditious and dangerous to the Government. Now when they are, and when they are not ſo (as the change of Circumſtances in the State may alter their Proſpect on it) the Government is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to judge than the Church, and when that thinks its Safety not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger'd by the toleration of them, ſhe is not for puniſhing them. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which Principle, by the ſame Reaſon that ſhe was for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Penal Laws formerly, ſhe may now be for their Repeal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Government thinks it ſelf ſafe without them. And this (I think) is almoſt the only thing wherein <hi>T. W.</hi> doth not Miſrepreſent her, That now ſhe is really for the Eaſe of Tender Conſciences; not (as he brings in her Enemies ſuggeſting, <hi>p.</hi> 12.) becauſe ſhe wants Power to Oppreſs, but becauſe the change of Circumſtances in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49539:11"/>makes the Opinions of Diſſenters, whether Proteſtant or Popiſh, not ſo dangerous to the Peace of the State, or the Authority of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Powers, as formerly they have been. And this ſhe may modeſtly conclude, because the King and his Council have thought fit to Indulge them, whoſe Intereſt obliges them to be moſt Impartial, and whoſe Experience in State Affairs makes them moſt able to judge of ſuch things.</p>
            <p>The State was then in ſuch real or imaginary Dangers as it is not now; The Succeſſion of the King to the Crown is not now in Diſpute, nor is Dominion believ'd to be founded in Grace, if ſuch Times ſhould come again, the old Severities might be ſoon reinforced: Whilſt we are in no danger of them, let us put them into a Condition of Eaſe and Safety frankly, that they may have no juſt Prejudice againſt us or our Religion, and that the King, who is intitled to the Service of every Subject of his, of what Perſuaſion ſoever, by the Law of Nature, and the Common Law of the Land (of which no Act or Parliament can, or ought to bar him) may make uſe of their Perſons and Services, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Diſcretion. Why ſhould not his Catholic Subjects be equally capacitated to render him Service, and be united with us in the ſame Bonds of Duty and Allegiance, tho' they cannot accord with us in Matters of Religion? Why ſhould we ſhew ſo much Violence in thoſe Points of Faith, of which, perhaps, we can ſhew no certain Evidence? The decrepit World, in the twilight of its declining Age, may be eaſily miſtaken in the Colours of Good and Evil, true or falſe. Their Merits have been great of the Crown, and their Sufferings more than Ours, and why then ſhould we repine, to ſee the long deſerv'd, &amp; deferr'd Rewards of their Loyalty conferr'd upon them at laſt? Let our onely Emulation be who ſhall ſerve him beſt. Princes are not to be Catechis'd in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Honors or Offices, nor could we think he had any true Zeal for his Religion, if he ſhould not countenance and preſerve them, at leaſt <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> with others, if not before them. Suppoſe our repining ſhould provoke him to turn the Tables upon us, and to employ no Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or Servants about him but <hi>Roman-Catholics,</hi> whom could we reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably blame but our ſelves. Let the King unite them and us in one Camp and Court in God's Name, and let there always be a Religious Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence between them and us in the Service of ſo great and ſo good a Maſter. To diſpute his Power in this Caſe, were to deny him the choice of his Servants, which we ſhould think a Wrong to the meaneſt of us to be depriv'd of; and alſo to rob him of the Militia of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49539:11"/>to diminiſh his Regal Authority, and to deprive him of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of a great part of his Subjects, from which no Act of Parliament can reſtrain him, becauſe the Law of Nature gives it him.</p>
            <p>As to the Men of <hi>Taunton</hi> and <hi>Tiverton,</hi> who were formerly Stigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd for their Rebellion, they are now the more eminent for return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Loyalty, from which they made ſo notorious a Defection, and ſhould be embrac'd by us accordingly with great joy, as returning Prodigals. And ſome of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who were formerly known to be accompliſh'd Men, of good Parts and Breeding, are with a <hi>Non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi> to their Religion, taken into his Majeſties Protection, for which they give him Thanks with a Grace that very well becomes them; which, as new a thing as it is, and as much as our Author is ſurpris'd at it, is not a thing utterly incredible. It is far from a Miracle to ſee ſo Gracious a Prince as King <hi>James</hi> the Second is, to cheriſh and reward the Loyalty of his Subjects Hearts in ſpite of their Hats, or their more ſhameful Miſtakes in Matters of Religion. The Princes Power is not limited to his moroſe Humor; He can, as oft as he is ſo diſpos'd, be Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to them, who have been undutiful to him, Reprieve and Pardon whom he has juſtly Condemn'd, without acquainting him or the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor with the Reaſons of ſo ſudden &amp; effectual a Change, he may alter his own Mind without altering the Nature of other Things. If a Man repent of his Crimes and the King Pardon him, and he amend his Life in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to obtain God's Pardon too, our envious Author laments his entire Reſignation, and looks upon his Endeavors, now he is Converted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to ſtrengthen his Brethren, as an unwelcom Task, and looks upon them as ſqueez'd out of him by the weight of his being ſo obnoxious; by which he ſquints at a Perſon who has Honor and Courage enough to call him to an account for it, if he knew where his humble Servant <hi>T.W.</hi> were to be found, whom he believes to be better at his Pen, than any other Weapon.</p>
            <p>What he ſaith of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Provocations, <hi>p.</hi> 12. may be ſubſcrib'd to by all, as an Inſtance of her excellent Temper, if his Letter, which is an Exception againſt it, do not hinder, if yet there be any reaſon to blame her for the Raſhneſs and Indiſcretion of one of her Members, when the reſt bare the Reproches of ſo many malicious Pamphlets, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out quarrelling eithere the Government or the Diſſenters: Theſe Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations like a Storm of Hail upon a ſtrong Houſe, cauſe more Noiſe than Prejudice. She is ready (he ſaith <hi>pag.</hi> 13.) rather to ſuffer, than to receive all the Advantages that can be gain'd by a criminal Compliance, And if ſhe refuſe only criminal Compliances, I am perſuaded ſhe will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49539:12"/>never ſuffer under this merciful Prince, who requires no Man to play the Hypocrite, or act againſt his Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The Reflection, <hi>pag.</hi> 13. ſavors much of <hi>T. W</hi>'s Spirit, who cannot forbear Libelling the Government; for what ground hath he but his own Fancy to inſinuate, that the next Parliament will not be Elected freely, but by <hi>Conge d'Eſlire,</hi> and the Men Return'd whom the King nominates, whether Elected or no? And that when Return'd, they will not be allow'd the liberty to Debate freely in Parliament, but oblig'd, without Examination, to do whatever they are deſir'd. For doth not he in his very next Paragraph contradict himſelf? wherein he ſaith, that the Papiſts themſelves do not rely upon the Legality of the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and therefore are ſo very earneſt to get it Eſtabliſh'd by Law. For they are not ſo blind, but that they can ſee there will be no more Security in a Law made by a Parliament illegally choſen, and under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint in their Votes, than in a bare Declaration; and that the next Turn of Government would regard that leſs than this. So that if it be their Intereſt to have a Parliament to ſecure their Liberty by Law, it is equally their Intereſt to have one freely choſen, and free in their Votes. And what reaſon is there to ſuſpect Men will act contrary to what they know to be their Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Our Author knows who they were who were Return'd out of every Burrough, by virtue of the Letters Miſſive from the Faction in the City, and inſtead of Election were ſatisfi'd if they could get but a double Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, when the Power of the Committees of Election was more ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, and to worſe Purpoſes, than the King's <hi>Conge d'Eſlire;</hi> And whereas he farther ſuggeſts, that our Methods of Enacting Laws in <hi>England</hi> will be reduc'd to thoſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that the Papiſts ſhall be made Lords of the Articles over us, and yet endeavors to wheadle the Diſſenters into a fond Perſuaſion that the Parliament will offer them an Indulgence without including the Papiſts: To give him a Cooler for his Conceit, they have told him already, that this Way of his will catch none but Woodcocks, and that they can ſee and break thro' it at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſo his Road is quite ſpoil'd: And for our parts, the Church of <hi>England</hi> has taught us to value the Merit of Obedience above the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Debate, which ſuch Men as he would turn into Licenciouſneſs, and Liberty of Aſperſing, if not Altering the Government.</p>
            <p>What he inſinuates, <hi>pag.</hi> 15. of the danger, leſt if the King, and thoſe of his Communion, be gratifi'd by the legal Eſtabliſhment of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, they will at the next Step attempt theirs that helped them, and after the Diſſenters ſqueazineſs in ſtarting at a Surplice, force them to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49539:12"/>ſwallow Tranſubſtantiation, is another of thoſe malicious Suggeſtions, which have been ſufficiently Anſwer'd at the beginning of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, it looks like a Plot to pelt out the Proteſtant Religion with Sugar-plums, ſo ridiculous is it and unreaſonable. The ſum of all is, that <hi>T.W.</hi> pretends to be an Ambaſſador from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to invite the Diſſenters to joyn with her in a League againſt the <hi>Roman-Catholics,</hi> promiſing every one Liberty when the Parliament meets, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only the King and thoſe of his Religion: which makes me to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion his Credentials, and ſuſpect him for a Cheat, ſince all the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have their Good Breeding better bounded, than to be civil and obliging to all Men but their Prince.</p>
            <p>He is like a Man in a Trance, rapt into the Religious Cauſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> none knows how; he blames her Sons for going too far in compliance with the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and yet complains, that they are not only deſerted, but proſecuted, but when and how he leaves us to gueſs; nor do we know what Weight of Power it is they lie under to avoid the Burden of being Criminal; which whilſt he maliciouſly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts, he ſpeaks like Council Retain'd by his old Friends the <hi>Republicans</hi> in <hi>Forty Eight,</hi> againſt the Prerogative, which has done nothing yet in this King's Reign or his Predeceſſor's, to fall thus under his Diſpleaſure. Our Gracious Sovereign hath already done more for our Church, than the moſt ſanguine of her Sons ever look'd for, which gives us reaſon to believe that he will never be ſorry for doing what we deſir'd. <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is more than pretended to be given by him, and yet there is no Freedom or Property to be ſacrific'd for it neither, as far as yet appears, or we believe is ever like to do. The King intends not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinge the Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for that he can no more do, than he can be unfaithful; He only deſires Safety, and the Protection of the Laws for thoſe of his own Communion, and other Diſſenters too, which (however peeviſh Men may be, at the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) will appear ſo reaſonable upon ſecond and more ſedate Thoughts, that however (<hi>p.</hi> 17.) the odds be Two hundred to one in the number of us and them, yet there will be no ſuch odds in the Votes for and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Indulgence.</p>
            <p>I am as loth as he is, that we ſhould throw away all Human Means of preſerving our Religion (<hi>p.</hi> 17.) and I doubt not but that the Wiſdom of the Nation may find Human Expedients to ſecure it to us, without Infringing the natural Liberty of Subjects by ſevere Teſts, or tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing over their Conſciences by Penal Laws. Sure I am, a peeviſh provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a Prince, whoſe Spirit and Power are equally great, is no Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Means of its Preſervation.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49539:13"/>
            <p>Our Author's great fear is, that the Thankers of the King will be Repealers of the Teſt in the next Parliament, which would bring them under ſuch a Scandal as would make them odious to all Mankind; from which that he may the better deter them, he tells them, that by reſcuing themſelves from the ſeverity of one Law, they will neceſſarily give a blow to all the reſt, and that the Price of their Liberty will be no leſs than the giving up their Right in all the Laws, which were a loſing Bargain indeed, to draw ſuch a Miſchief as this upon themſelves. But whether thoſe Methods which he propoſes to them, will not more infallibly deſtroy them, I hope the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and the Church of <hi>England</hi> men will conſider well, before they follow them, It concerns us all to take heed, that in acting for the preſervation of our Religion, we do not expoſe it to more imminent and apparent danger.</p>
            <q>Tanti non eſt ut placeam Tibi perire. <bibl>
                  <hi>Martial.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>If nothing will gratifie our Author but what will diſpleaſe and diſſerve the King, let his Pretexts be never ſo ſpecious, he ſhall not intice us into a ſinful Compliance, we will follow the Golden Rule, to do to others as we would have them do to us in like Circumſtances.</p>
            <q>Arma tenenti, omnia dat qui juſta negat.</q>
            <p>Our obſtinate and unſeaſonable ſtiffneſs hath made ſome Alterations already in Public Affairs and Adminiſtrations, and may provoke his Majeſty to do thoſe things in his Diſpleaſure, which may be more prejudicial to our Religion than the Repealing of the Teſt can be, the making whereof ſhe abhorr'd and oppos'd as much as ſhe could, and cannot remember the Author or Occaſion of it without Deteſtation. And I hope the King's <hi>Old</hi> Friends will not put the King to ſuch ſhameful Shifts, as to fly to his <hi>New</hi> for any Juſtice they can do him in this or any other kind. If they ſhould fail of their Duty in this kind, their Mother Church will not bleſs them, nor be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd to ſee the Father of the Country correct ſuch ill-nurtur'd Children as are too big for her Diſcipline. I queſtion not but that the next Parliament will do what the King and all good Subjects expect from them. The King is aſſur'd of the Affections of his People in groſs, they have already Preſented him with their Lives and Fortunes in their repeated weekly Addreſſes, and therefore he will be ſure to find it by their Loyal Repreſentatives, who will never ſail to give him that Satisfaction in a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary way, which they have already done in a Popular one; for they would wrong us as well as him, if they ſhould not give him that Satisfaction in Formalities of Law, which our Devotion hath already deſign'd and dedicated to him. All true Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> rejoyce, and are pleas'd in his Majeſties Government, and doubt not but a good Correſpondence between him and his two next Houſes of Parliament will put the Ballance of <hi>Europe</hi> into his Hands; but if once a Spirit of Jealouſie ſhould be rais'd between him and us, to fright us from the Repealing of the Teſt and Penal Laws, what Diſadvantages may accrue to our Nation or our Religion, I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think. We had need do ſomething more than ordinary, to atone for the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood that has been ſhed upon the Teſtimony of a few perjur'd Villains.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I have given you my Opinion of the Pamphlet you ſent me, which was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly writ with a very ill Deſign againſt the King, &amp; no good Intention for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whom it repreſents (as it would perſuade her to be) obſtinately engag'd, not only againſt the Religion, but againſt the Intereſt of her Prince too, attempting to draw Men to ſuſpect his Mercy for Treachery, and inviting Diſſenters to Combine againſt his Gracious Deſigns for the Eaſe of all his Subjects; which I am perſuaded the Church of <hi>England</hi> by her Compliances without obſtinacy, as far as without deſerting her Religion ſhe may, will in the Event demonſtrate to be black-mouth'd Calumnies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
